<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>tangarts - Review</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/review.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2020-12-26T11:09:52+00:00</updated><entry><title>2020: A Year in Review</title><link href="/2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-26T11:09:52+00:00</updated><author><name>Nehemiah Tang-Campbell</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-11-29:/2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The year of connection, I've decided on the theme for next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, how did the year of creating go?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In exploring this years theme I managed to create a personal CRM, starting with
a &lt;a href="https://sive.rs/dbt"&gt;personal database&lt;/a&gt;, expanded functionality with Django
and a web interface.&lt;br&gt;
I highly recommend …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The year of connection, I've decided on the theme for next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, how did the year of creating go?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In exploring this years theme I managed to create a personal CRM, starting with
a &lt;a href="https://sive.rs/dbt"&gt;personal database&lt;/a&gt;, expanded functionality with Django
and a web interface.&lt;br&gt;
I highly recommend looking at &lt;a href="https://www.monicahq.com/"&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt; for a complete,
maintained project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also tinkered with Common Lisp during the summer, published only 10 posts
since choosing the theme, there is still time! My list of unpublished &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt;
increased and the frequency of note taking increased too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has helped as I moved to learning Clojure and ClojureScript for 
&lt;em&gt;real world projects&lt;/em&gt;, learning React via ClojureScript's
&lt;em&gt;Reagent&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Re-frame&lt;/em&gt; libraries. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the summer I managed to read more than a &lt;a href="bookshelf"&gt;handful of books&lt;/a&gt;.
Late spring saw me invest more time into reading, learning, discovering
interesting things on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I hoped to have written 100 tweets in 3 months.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That didn't last long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I committed to writing more.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set my yearly theme to creating. Whilst I barely managed to publish a blog
post one every month it wasn't a goal to stick to a regime. Now, of course,
writing every morning, I don't need to be as conscious of what I type, the
content is for my eyes only. In the pile of offhand morning pages I have no
doubt there will be something I feel compelled to put up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I emailed an internet stranger for the first time&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an important turning point in the year, realizing the 
&lt;a href="mailto:nehemiahcampbell@hotmail.co.uk"&gt;feel free to email&lt;/a&gt;
wasn't just a modern curtsy, we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; want to hear from our audience and experts
are willing to reply to your queries. Being online is far more rewarding
when you interact with people on the other end of the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less lurking, more posting next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What else?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First internship. It was great working with &lt;a href="https://eng2eng.net/"&gt;E2E&lt;/a&gt;;
working on adding features to their online engineering network. The founders
are incredible leaders and I have no doubt they will have a successful career
ahead of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="sunset"&gt;Travel&lt;/a&gt;. I was lucky enough to survive the first exodus of exchange
students across Hong Kong. I spent the end of 2019 and beginning of 2020 in
Malaysia, Singapore and Vietnam. The remaining time in Hong Kong was quiet,
a drop in tourists and familiar faces hadn't returned over the holiday.&lt;br&gt;
My intentional visit home mid March turned into an unexpected end to my time 
in Hong Kong. Even though I miss the excitement of travelling, I made the most
of my time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my personal life I finally had the courage to ask someone out. In the five
months I have been with her I have learnt how to be more forgiving, not to
assume the worst possible outcome and realizing that life is not forever so
enjoy the present. Earlier this year I concluded that regrets are something
I do not have, only lessons to be learnt from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2020 wasn't &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; bad, could've been worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello 2021. More on that later.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Review"></category></entry><entry><title>The Year of Creating</title><link href="/the-year-of-creating.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Nehemiah Tang-Campbell</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-01-29:/the-year-of-creating.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;It's not too late for new years resolutions!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lunar_calendar"&gt;New Years&lt;/a&gt; have arrived
and I'm still without a goal to chase. An accomplishment to achieve by the end
of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the CGP Grey video I have decided to make it the year of creating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resolutions are hard rules …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;It's not too late for new years resolutions!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lunar_calendar"&gt;New Years&lt;/a&gt; have arrived
and I'm still without a goal to chase. An accomplishment to achieve by the end
of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the CGP Grey video I have decided to make it the year of creating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resolutions are hard rules to follow.  Humans aren't too good at sticking to
hard rules.  Instead, yearly themes are substituted as a way of defining our
yearly goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty of themes is that they aren't strictly defined. This plays well with
ever changing goals and circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So why creating?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months, I have been meaning to improve my ability to communicate well
through writing. So far, not much has been produced in terms of publishable
content. I hope to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increase the amount of written files I produce.&lt;/strong&gt; Whether that is on daily
  entries on how I feel, technical topics accessible to anyone literate or an
  interesting insight that I would like to review and document in my own words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Refine and edit new and existing pieces.&lt;/strong&gt; Removing unnecessary words. Not
  being afraid of reading material from my past self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will be an interesting to see where the year of creativity will take me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What goals will I have achieved and how will I define creating in 12 months.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To a year of creating!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Review"></category></entry></feed>